<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>

  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>You don’t need to be an expert web developer to build web apps. With
  Dart, you can be productive as you build high-performance apps for the
  modern web.</para>

  <para>Our aim for this book is to be a useful introduction to the Dart
  language, libraries, and tools. Because this book is short and Dart is
  young, you might also need to refer to the Dart website at <ulink
  url="http://dartlang.org"></ulink>—both for details and for updates. For the
  latest news, keep an eye on the <ulink
  url="http://google.com/+dartlang">Dart page</ulink> on Google+.</para>

  <para>Another important website is this book’s <ulink
  url="https://github.com/dart-lang/dart-up-and-running-book">GitHub
  project.</ulink> The text for this work is available there under the <ulink
  url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/">Creative Commons
  Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 United States
  License.</ulink> Source code files for this book’s samples are also there,
  in the <ulink
  url="https://github.com/dart-lang/dart-up-and-running-book/tree/master/code"><literal>code/</literal></ulink>
  subdirectory. Downloading the sample code from GitHub is much easier than
  copying it from the book.</para>

  <para>If you find an error in the sample code or text, please <ulink
  url="https://github.com/dart-lang/dart-up-and-running-book/issues/new">create
  an issue.</ulink></para>

  <sect1 id="preface-conventions">
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this
    book:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Italic</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indicates new terms, URLs, email addresses, filenames, and
          file extensions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal moreinfo="none">Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for program listings, as well as within paragraphs to
          refer to program elements such as variable or function names,
          databases, data types, environment variables, statements, and
          keywords.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><userinput moreinfo="none">Constant width
        bold</userinput></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally by
          the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied values
          or by values determined by context.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <tip>
      <para>This icon signifies a tip, suggestion, or general note.</para>
    </tip>

    <caution>
      <para>This icon indicates a warning or caution.</para>
    </caution>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preface-examples">
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>

    <para>This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may
    use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You do not
    need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant
    portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several
    chunks of code from this book does not require permission. Selling or
    distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require
    permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example
    code does not require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of
    example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require
    permission.</para>

    <para>We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution
    usually includes the <phrase role="keep-together">title, author,</phrase>
    publisher, and ISBN. For example: “<emphasis>Dart:Up and
    Running</emphasis> by Kathy Walrath and Seth Ladd (O’Reilly). Copyright
    2013 Kathy Walrath and Seth Ladd, 978-1-449-33089-7.”</para>

    <para>If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the
    permission given above, feel free to contact us at
    <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preface-safari">
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>

    <note role="safarienabled">
      <para>Safari Books Online (<ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital"
      url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">www.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>)
      is an on-demand digital library that delivers expert <ulink
      role="orm:hideurl"
      url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/content">content</ulink> in both
      book and video form from the world’s leading authors in technology and
      business.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Technology professionals, software developers, web designers, and
    business and creative professionals use Safari Books Online as their
    primary resource for research, problem solving, learning, and
    certification training.</para>

    <para>Safari Books Online offers a range of <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/subscriptions">product mixes</ulink>
    and pricing programs for <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/organizations-teams">organizations</ulink>,
    <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/government">government
    agencies</ulink>, and <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/individuals">individuals</ulink>.
    Subscribers have access to thousands of books, training videos, and
    prepublication manuscripts in one fully searchable database from
    publishers like O’Reilly Media, Prentice Hall Professional, Addison-Wesley
    Professional, Microsoft Press, Sams, Que, Peachpit Press, Focal Press,
    Cisco Press, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Syngress, Morgan Kaufmann, IBM
    Redbooks, Packt, Adobe Press, FT Press, Apress, Manning, New Riders,
    McGraw-Hill, Jones &amp; Bartlett, Course Technology, and dozens <ulink
    role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/publishers">more</ulink>. For more
    information about Safari Books Online, please visit us <ulink
    role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/">online</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preface-contact">
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para>Please address comments and questions concerning this book to the
    publisher:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>

      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>

      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>

      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>

      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>

      <member>707-829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>We have a web page for this book, where we list errata, examples,
    and any additional information. You can access this page at <ulink
    url="http://oreil.ly/Dart_Up_and_Running"></ulink>.</para>

    <para>To comment or ask technical questions about this book, send email to
    <email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>

    <para>For more information about our books, courses, conferences, and
    news, see our website at <ulink
    url="http://www.oreilly.com"></ulink>.</para>

    <para>Find us on Facebook: <ulink
    url="http://facebook.com/oreilly"></ulink></para>

    <para>Follow us on Twitter: <ulink
    url="http://twitter.com/oreillymedia"></ulink></para>

    <para>Watch us on YouTube: <ulink
    url="http://www.youtube.com/oreillymedia"></ulink></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preface-updates">
    <title>Content Updates</title>

    <para>We’ve updated the content to reflect the following changes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Using <literal>part of</literal> in additional library files is
        now <emphasis>required</emphasis>, not optional.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In M2, several APIs changed:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the dart:html library, the <literal>elements</literal>
            property of Element is now called
            <literal>children</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Names in dart:html have changed to conform to Dart naming
            standards. In particular, <literal>innerHTML</literal> is now
            <literal>innerHtml</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <literal>charCodes()</literal> method of String is now a
            getter, so we removed the parentheses from all references to
            <literal>charCodes</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <literal>readAsText()</literal> method of File is now
            called <literal>readAsString()</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Constructors for the Date class have changed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>NullPointerException no longer exists.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RegExp no longer has a const constructor.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The return type of StringBuffer's <literal>add()</literal>
            method changed to void. Code that used to chain calls to
            <literal>add()</literal> should now use method cascades
            instead.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The recommended way for web apps to use
        <literal>dart.js</literal> is now to have a local copy, preferably one
        downloaded using the <literal>browser</literal> pub package.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The core libraries were revised in M3. Changes include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Some methods have changed to fields or getters. This meant
            we had to remove the <literal>()</literal> after
            <literal>hashCode</literal>, <literal>isEmpty</literal> and
            <literal>isNan</literal>. We also changed
            <literal>getKeys()</literal> to <literal>keys</literal>, and
            <literal>getValues()</literal> to
            <literal>values</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Iterable class has been beefed up, affecting all
            Collections such as Lists and Sets. The former Collection methods
            <literal>filter()</literal> and <literal>map()</literal> are now
            in Iterable, and the name of <literal>filter()</literal> has
            changed to <literal>where()</literal>. (<literal>map()</literal>
            was briefly renamed to <literal>mappedBy()</literal>, but due to
            public feedback that decision was reversed.) The
            <literal>some()</literal> method is now named
            <literal>any()</literal>. Many values returned by Iterables are
            now lazily filled Iterables; you can use
            <literal>toList()</literal> or <literal>toSet()</literal> to force
            evaluation. We recommend <emphasis>extending</emphasis> Iterable
            rather than just implementing it, so you can take advantage of
            added functionality. More details are in an article, <ulink
            url="http://www.dartlang.org/articles/m3-whats-new/iterables.html">Iterables</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Iterator interface has changed from
            <literal>next()</literal> and <literal>hasNext()</literal> to
            <literal>current</literal> and
            <literal>moveNext()</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dart:json library no longer has a JSON class. Former
            JSON static methods such as <literal>parse()</literal> and
            <literal>stringify()</literal> are now top-level functions.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date is now named DateTime, and the
            <literal>fromString()</literal> constructor is now a static method
            named <literal>parse()</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Event handler registration used to be
            <literal>.on.<replaceable>event</replaceable>.add()</literal>; now
            it’s
            <literal>.on<replaceable>Event</replaceable>.listen()</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dart:html HttpRequest <literal>get()</literal> method
            has been replaced by <literal>getString()</literal> and
            <literal>request()</literal>, which return Future&lt;String&gt;
            and Future&lt;HttpRequest&gt;, respectively.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dart:html Window <literal>setTimeout()</literal> method
            is gone; instead, use a Timer.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Timer and Completer have moved from dart:isolate to a new
            library called dart:async. The Timer constructors now take a
            Duration instead of an int.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Future <literal>chain()</literal> and
            <literal>handleException()</literal> methods are gone, replaced by
            <literal>then()</literal> and
            <literal>catchError()</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>We’ve also added discussions for a few pre-existing features:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Lexical scope (see <xref linkend="ch02-lexical-scope" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>… <remark>[PENDING: more?]</remark></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preface-acknowledgments">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>

    <para>We’d like to thank the many people who contributed to this book. We
    hope we haven’t forgotten anyone, but we probably have.</para>

    <para>The following Dart engineers and managers gave us prompt, helpful
    reviews of the sections corresponding to their areas of responsibility:
    Mads Ager, Peter von der Ahé, Justin Fagnani, Dan Grove, Florian Loitsch,
    Sam McCall, Vijay Menon, John Messerly, Anton Muhin, Lasse R.H. Nielsen,
    Bob Nystrom, Ivan Posva, and Jaime Wren.</para>

    <para>We’d especially like to thank the people who reviewed even bigger
    swaths of the book or contributed in other, large ways:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>JJ Behrens, whose careful look at the first draft of the book
        helped us catch errors and inconsistencies, as well as rework Chapter
        5 to be more interesting, and less of a laundry list. He also created
        a system for testing our samples, so we can be sure that they work now
        and continue to work as the language and libraries evolve.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shailen Tuli, who helped test our examples although he didn’t
        even work for Google.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mary Campione, whose stream-of-consciousness review of the
        entire book, performed while she was first learning the language,
        helped us find and fix many confusing spots, as well as some
        errors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Phil Quitslund, who did a big-picture review of the book and
        gave us guidance and encouragement.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Kasper Lund, whose review caught issues that only someone with
        his expert, comprehensive knowledge of the Dart language and libraries
        could have found.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Gilad Bracha, the language spec writer whose reviews of the
        language chapter (our longest one) were invaluable for getting
        language details right. We couldn’t cover everything, so we look
        forward to his future work on making all the corners of the language
        understandable to all Dart programmers.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Other Googlers helped, as well. Vivian Li, the head of Chrome
    Developer Relations, supported our work on this book. Andres Ferrate, the
    Google Press liaison to O’Reilly, helped simplify the process of getting
    the book published. Myisha Harris gave us excellent legal advice.</para>

    <para>The people at O’Reilly were extremely helpful. Meghan Blanchette,
    our editor, kept everything going smoothly, monitoring our progress in the
    nicest possible way. Christopher Hearse checked our work and helped us
    make some last-minute fixes that improved the final result. We’d also like
    to thank the good people who manage the author workflow and make working
    on an O’Reilly book such a pleasure. We personally worked with Sarah
    Schneider and Jessica Hosman.</para>

    <para>Finally, we thank Lars Bak and Kasper Lund for writing the foreword,
    and most of all for creating Dart.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>